<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jason Jabbour - Project Management</title><link href="Https:/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https:///feeds/project-management.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>Https:/</id><updated>2019-07-11T16:07:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>How Kanban Increased My Efficiency</title><link href="https:///how-kanban-increased-my-efficiency.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-11T16:07:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-11T16:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jason Jabbour</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-07-11:/how-kanban-increased-my-efficiency.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How Kanban Increased My Efficiency&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="trello" src="{filename}../output/coffee-communication-connection-1181494.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working in the payroll industry as an implementation manager for over five years now and frequently wished for a better way to organize ongoing projects. It’s not uncommon for my team and I to have five or six projects that need …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How Kanban Increased My Efficiency&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="trello" src="{filename}../output/coffee-communication-connection-1181494.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working in the payroll industry as an implementation manager for over five years now and frequently wished for a better way to organize ongoing projects. It’s not uncommon for my team and I to have five or six projects that need work simultaneously. In the beginning when the company was smaller and everyone worked in the office, we kept it simple by using a whiteboard to keep track of it all. Then as our company expanded, people started working remotely and clients needed more, we found ourselves scrambling to come up with a system that met all our needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we struggled to find rhyme and reason in our day to day work demands, I began using a cheat sheet that I wrote up that was ten pages of implementation pinpoints. It was helpful in the fact that it was a way to pass on information to coworkers but the method of having to scan the copy each time was tedious and a big time waster. Quickly desks began to be buried underneath piles of papers clipped together that we would have to sift through to gather information. It was frustrating to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second half of 2018 came and I needed a change. Printing reams of paper just to scan and shred them was no longer working. Our clients were becoming more complex and because of that staying organized was getting tougher. In addition to work, I began to study for the PMP certification and truly needed a way to keep organized. I discovered through my studies the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban"&gt;Kanban methodology&lt;/a&gt;. The Kanban method is a way of pinpointing the items needed in a project and designating whether they need to be done, are currently being worked on or completed. One would use what is called a Kanban board to keep track of these items as they go along. One useful tool that I stumbled upon is the web site &lt;a href="https://trello.com/en-US"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt;. You can use your Google log in to set up an account and can create as many boards as you need to stay organized. What I ended up doing was creating a generic board that can be applied to the majority of my implementation projects. The most exciting part to all of this was that I was able to take what I was learning in my spare time and apply it to my real life working situation and see results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literally, in the span of an afternoon I was able to convert my now fifteen page “conversion cheat sheet” into a Kanban board. It took a couple clients to work out the kinks since the cheat sheet was the tool I used for a few years. But once I was able to convert our workflow from one tool to the next my efficiency skyrocketed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing I instantly liked about the Kanban methodology was how visual it was. As a visual learner, using Kanban instantly appealed to me because without much effort you can see what projects have been started, completed and what’s currently in progress. I can see that I set up a certain portion of my client without having to thumb through pages of notes to make sure I had done everything I needed to. It also gave a sense of progress that I sometimes lacked with our older method. Especially on clients that span a couple months to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often found that when I had multiple projects going at the same time I was overwhelmed at times and also felt like the project wasn't going as quickly as it should be. There was no visualization of my progress being made. Sure there were a few boxes checked but on a macro level it was tough to see where I stood. Even with the best time management it was easy to get lost and spend more time on one client and less on another. Before I knew it I was ahead on some projects and way behind on others. With the Kanban method, I can open my board and see exactly what needs to be done without having to do much legwork. I could also get that sense of accomplishment when I check all of my current boards and can see I’m close to the finish line. The last thing I can say that I like about the Kanban method is that it's not only me who can see where I stand at a glance within a project, but my teammates can too. If I am out on vacation for example, my teammates can pick up right where I left off easily. When I am back in the office from my Caribbean vacation, I can also pick things back up from them and know exactly what was done while I was out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem simple, but using the Kanban method has kept me organized and has given me back precious time in my day. Not having to thumb through checklists or scan and shred piles of paper adds up in at the end of the week when you wished you had one more hour to finish things up before the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href="https://www.pexels.com/@divinetechygirl"&gt;Christina Morillo&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://www.pexels.com/"&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>